Guide toa the Mary F. Lopez Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Mary F. Lopez Papers
1942-2014
2000-2008
04/2014-006
Lopez, Mary F., 1921-2015
0.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The collection is approximately .5 linear feet and consists primarily of documents, correspondence, organization records, photographs and clippings. A significant part of the collection is comprised of photocopies.
Biographical Information:
Mary Fernandez Lopez was born Mary Fernandez on September 26, 1921 in Brownsville, Texas, but would spend most of her life in Houston. It was in Houston where she would marry, have four children, and participate in social justice issues related to Hispanic Americans.
Mary wed Jose Rivera Lopez on May 17, 1942 at Camp Blanding near the city of Starke, Florida shortly after he joined the Army. The couple lived briefly in Massachusetts before returning to Houston and starting a family in 1943. Primarily a homemaker until her children were raised, Ms. Lopez was consistently involved in advocating for the Mexican-American community in the Magnolia Park.
After working mainly secretarial positions Bovay Enginnering and later University of Texas Medical Branch, Mary graduated with her business degree from the University of Houston. For a time, she also helped manage her family’s business, the Lopez Bakery in Magnolia Park before selling it in the 1960s.
Lopez was involved with the Viva-Kennedy Campaign, the Political Association for Spanish Speaking Organizations (PASO), and other efforts related to improving conditions for Houston’s Latino community. Mary F. Lopez died in July 2015.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Photographs
Geographic Name:
Houston (Tex.) -- History; Magnolia Park, TX
Topical Term:
Hispanic American women -- Texas -- Houston
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Related Materials:
Mary F. Lopez Papers digital collection http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/2014_006
Scope and Contents
The collection is approximately .5 linear feet and consists primarily of documents, correspondence, organization records, photographs and clippings. A significant part of the collection is comprised of photocopies.
Organized into two series, Series I, Jose R. Lopez Papers, and Series II, Mary F. Lopez Papers, the collection includes materials related to Ms. Mary F. Lopez life as a homemaker, wife, activist, and her career.
Documents related to Mr. Jose R. Lopez’s time in WWII are of note, as are photographs of Cesar Chavez in series II. Ms. Lopez met Chavez in the 1960s during one of his visits in support of Mexican-American labor in the region.
Detailed List of Contents
- Jose R. Lopez Papers
  - Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Discharge Documents, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - War Claims Commission, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Award of Disability or Pension, February 14, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial Documents, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Certificate of Death, January 4, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ephemera (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A unit roster for Company M, 142nd Infantry Regiment, 36th Division of the U. S. Amy (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Prisoners of War Bulletin, August 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rotate Review, October 15, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Prisoner of War Bulletin (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The T-Patcher Newsletter, Summer 2012 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Mary F. Lopez Papers
  - Career
    - Letters of Recommendation and Applications, 1969-2007 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Clippings and Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Work-related Publications and Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Marriage
    - Marriage Records, 1942, 1953, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Activism
    - Correspondence and Clippings, undated, 1958-2014 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Activist Publications and Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Harris Country PASO Fact Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous Publications and Notes, undated, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Voter Registration Materials, 2002-2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Photographs with Cesar Chavez, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)